Guide to the Records of the Italian-American Labor Council WAG 091
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Italian-American Labor Council Records
1941-1996
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Italian-American Labor Council
WAG 091
5 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
The Italian-American Labor Council (IALC) was formed in direct response to Mussolini's declaration of war against the United States in 1941. It lobbied successfully against the implementation of the Enemy Alien Act of 1942 which designated all German, Italian and Japanese nationals as enemy aliens. In the years after the Second World War, the IALC organized aid for post-war Italy. In the 1950s, it also played an instrumental role in forming the "Free Labor Movement" that opposed the Italian Communists and Communist-orientated labor organizations. These records include operational materials, clippings and correspondence of the IALC from its founding in 1941 to 1996.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Italian-American Labor Council in 1992 and 1997. The accession number associated with this gift is 1992.008.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
On December 20, 1941, the Italian-American Labor Council (IALC) was formed in direct response to Mussolini's declaration of war against the United States, which had occurred ten days earlier. Although the IALC was formed in direct response to Fascism, its roots illustrate the dramatic narrative of the Italian-Americans and their rise within the organized labor movement.
Since the nineteenth century, through persistent political exertion, Italian-American labor leaders have transformed the initially disunited groups of Italian-American workers into a united force within organized labor. Such leaders as Salvatore Ninfo, Arturo Giovannitti, Carlo Tresca, and Joseph Catalanotti, who would later become founding members of the IALC, orchestrated these early efforts. From 1913 to 1919, for example, the Italian-Americans in the garment trades in New York City developed three powerful locals: Local 63 (Italian Coatmakers) of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America (ACWA) headed by Augusto Bellanca, and Locals 48 (Italian Coatmakers) and 89 (Italian Dressmakers) of the International Ladies Garment Workers Union (ILGWU), led respectively by Eduardo Molisani and Luigi Antonini. Antonini would later become the pivotal force behind the founding of the IALC.
Antonini's rise to the top of the Italian-American labor movement did not occur overnight. In 1934, he became the ILGWU's first vice-president under president David Dubinsky. Dubinsky, who was Treasurer of the Jewish Labor Committee (JLC), encouraged Antonini to take up the cause of the Italian trade unionists and form the IALC. The IALC and the JLC have continued to act as fraternal allies, coordinating activities and sharing resources. By 1940, Local 89 had 33,500 members and could stake a claim as one of the largest union locals in the United States. During this period, Antonini utilized weekly broadcasts entitled Voce della Locale 89 (Voice of Local 89) along with the Italian-language edition of the ILGWU's newspaper, Giustizia, to extend his influence among Italian-American workers. Antonini's sway over the Local 89 membership remained the source of his power and placed him at the top of Italian-American labor leadership at the outbreak of World War II.
On December 10, 1941, three days after the bombing of Pearl Harbor, Mussolini declared war on the United States. Italian-Americans were shocked. They now had to face the reality that their country of origin was at war with their adopted homeland. Adding to this emotional burden, they also faced an uncertain future because the newly instituted Enemy Alien Act threatened to restrict and possibly imprison those individuals who were not citizens. In response to these circumstances, the IALC leadership met for the first time on December 20, 1941. They chose as their slogan, "America's Victory is Italy's Freedom." At the end of its first year, the IALC could claim affiliates with a membership of 300,000 workers.
The first act of the IALC was to lobby successfully, on behalf of Italian-Americans, against the implementation of the Enemy Alien Act of 1942, which designated all German, Italian and Japanese nationals as enemy aliens. Italian-Americans found themselves facing the possibility of a massive evacuation from the east and west coasts of the United States to confinement in the Mid-West. In order to emphasize Italian-American loyalty to America, the IALC organized a "Freedom Rally" at Madison Square Garden on January 31, 1942. Twenty-two thousand people attended this assembly.
The IALC also engaged in practical political lobbying. The IALC was the first organization to put forward a proposal for the "exoneration of Italians from the category of Enemy Alien." In late spring 1942, Antonini went to Washington, D.C. and met with FBI Director, J. Edgar Hoover and Attorney General Francis Biddle. Through Antonini's collaborative efforts with Biddle, Italian-Americans were completely exempted from the Enemy Alien category. For his efforts in removing the enemy alien stigma from 600,000 Italian-Americans, Attorney General Biddle, in 1943, became the first recipient of the IALC's Four Freedoms Award. This citation was created to honor "meritorious services rendered to the cause of liberty among the people throughout the world." During this period, the IALC also raised funds for the Italian resistance movement and facilitated the settlement of Italian refugees.
In 1943, a deep political division formed within the IALC. One faction included those individuals who refused to work with the Communists. This group formed the American Committee for Italian Democracy and remained a part of the IALC. The second bloc covered those workers who accepted the Communists. This camp organized the Free Italy Labor Council. These factions reunited in 1958.
In the years after the Second World War, the IALC organized clothing drives and fundraising events for a war-ravaged Italy. In the 1950s, it also played an instrumental role in forming the "Free Labor Movement" that opposed the Italian Communists and Communist-orientated labor organizations. They have continued to act as interpreters of Italian politics for United States governmental officials and have also served as communicators of American labor policy to Italian trade unionists. The organization has organized official delegations, educational missions and good-will tours to Italy, and has regularly hosted visits from Italian political, labor and cultural leaders. The IALC has served as a bridge between the Italian and U.S. labor movements, as the voice of labor in the Italian-American community, and as a sponsor of philanthropic, cultural and political interchange between the two countries.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Italian American Labor Council span the years 1941-1996. The records consist of IALC Conference Proceedings, minutes of the Executive Board and Board of Directors (1941-1995), "Four Freedoms" awards, materials from tours to Italy, correspondence, newspaper clippings, and pamphlets. The records document the organization's founding, activities, commemoration celebrations, and organizational life.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Constitutions, Bylaws and Minutes; II; General Files.
Series I is arranged chronologically and Series II is arranged alphabetically by subject.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
The Italian-American Labor Council: Origins, Conflicts, and Contributions" by Vincent J. Tirelli, in Fifty Years of Progress (New York: IALC, 1991). (In IALC Vertical File.)
John Stuart Crawford, Luigi Antonini: His Influence on Italian-American Relations (New York: Educational Dept., Italian Dressmakers' Union, Local 89, ILGWU, 1950).
Records of the Jewish Labor Committee.
Pamphlets and memorabilia of the IALC and ILGWU Local 89, in the Tamiment Library Vertical Files.
Related materials at other archives.
Luigi Antonini Correspondence, (1919-1968) in the International Ladies Garment Workers' Union Records (1906-1985), Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives, Cornell University
Luigi Antonini Papers (1926-1959), Immigration History Research Center, University of Minnesota
Italian-American Labor Movement Collection (1900-1974), Center for Migration Studies, New York, NY.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to the fragile nature of the original materials, researchers must use the microfilmed version of the minutes in Series I; microfilm call number is R-7458.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Labor unions |z Italy.; Italian Americans; Clothing workers |z United States.; Labor unions -- United States.; Pamphlets.; Proceedings.; Minutes (administrative records); World War, 1939-1945 |x Underground movements.; Correspondence.; Anti-fascist movements -- United States.; Clippings (information artifacts); Free Italy Labor Council (U.S.); Italian-American Labor Council
- Series I: Constitutions, Bylaws, and Minutes (1941-1995; arranged chronologically)., 70547
  Scope and Contents note
  This series is divided into two parts, minutes of Executive Board and minutes of General Membership meetings; each series reflects the varied internal and external political concerns of the council membership over the last fifty-five years. These minutes chronicle the IALC's role in repealing the Enemy Alien Act, the 1943 factional division with the IALC, fundraising activities for a war-torn Italy in the immediate post-1945 period, and financial and political support for Italian labor unions during the 1950s.
  - Constitution & Bylaws, 1941-1991; 70570 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes: General Membership, 1941-1945; 70569 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes: General Membership, 1946-1948; 70568 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes: General Membership, 1949-1957; 70567 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes: Executive Committee, 1942-1945; 70566 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minutes: Executive Committee, 1949-1954; 70565 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes: Executive Committee, 1955-1958; 70564 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes: Executive Committee, 1962-1964; 70563 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Minutes: Executive Committee, 1965-1966; 70562 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Minutes: Executive Committee, 1967-1970; 70561 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Minutes: Executive Committee, 1971-1972; 70560 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Minutes: Executive Committee, 1973-1975; 70559 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Minutes: Executive Committee, 1977-1978; 70558 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Minutes: Executive Committee, 1979; 70557 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Minutes: Executive Committee, 1982-1984; 70556 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Minutes: Executive Committee, 1985-1988; 70555 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Minutes: Executive Committee, 1987; 70554 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Minutes: Executive Committee, 1989-1995; 70553 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Minutes: Board of Directors, 1987; 70552 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Minutes: Board of Directors, 1988; 70551 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Minutes: Board of Directors, 1989; 70550 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Minutes: Board of Directors, 1990-1994; 70549 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Minutes: Joint Meeting Board of Directors/Executive Committee, 1990; 70548 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series II: General Files (1941-1996; arranged alphabetically)., 70401
  This series includes IALC correspondence with such American and Italian labor organizations as the AFL-CIO, ILGWU Local 89 and Confederazione Italiana Sindacati Lavoratori. This series also contains IALC Annual Conference reports, Four Freedoms Award, Luncheon materials, various council initiatives such as Italian earthquake relief fund drives, Italian scholarship grants, labor conference reports and Italian-American labor friendship trip records.
  - Activities [IALC], 1942-1944; 70546 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - ANSA, 1963-1979; 70545 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Alitalia: Correspondence, 1985; 70544 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Alitalia: Strike, 1993; 70543 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Alitalia: Strike, 1993; 70542 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - American Committee on Italian Migration, 1978-1996; 70541 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - AFL-CIO: Correspondence, 1989-1995; 70540 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - American Federation of Teachers, 1990-1995; 70539 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - American Institute for Free Labor Development, 1989-1991; 70538 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - American Labor ORT, 1973-1986; 70537 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Annual Conference Proceedings [IALC] (Printed), 1941-1969; 70536 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Annual Reports [IALC], 1945-1954; 70535 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Asian Free Labor Institute, 1988-1989; 70534 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Associazone Amicizia AItalia-Stati Uniti d'America", 1989-1992; 70533 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Board of Directors: Correspondence, 1988-1995; 70532 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Boys Town of Italy, 1977-1988; 70531 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Cabrini Health Care Center, 1978-1981; 70530 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Calandra Italian American Institute, 1992-1995; 70529 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Carrara, Mario, 1967-1977; 70528 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Casa Italiana, 1978-1979; 70527 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Center for Migration Studies, 1989; 70526 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Chapters: Correspondence, 1990-1996; 70525 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Citta del Ragazzo, 1975; 70524 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Clippings, 1978-1979; 70523 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Coalition of Italian-American Associations, Inc., 1983-1984; 70522 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Columbus Day Celebration, 1942; 70521 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Columbus Quincentennial U.S.A., 1982; 70520 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Comitati dell' Emigrazioni Italiana, 1986; 70519 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - CGIL: Scuola, 1993-1995; 70518 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Confederazione Italiana Sindacati Lavoratori, 1980-1990; 70517 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Confederazione Italiana Sindacati Lavoratori, 1991-1993; 70516 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - CISL, 1993-1995; 70515 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - CISL, 1996; 70514 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Conference: Global Economy Boom or Bust, Conference Papers, 1992; 70513 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Conference: Global Economy Boom or Bust, Preparations, 1992; 70512 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1981; 70511 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1982-1987; 70510 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1988-1995; 70509 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: CISL, INCA, 1994-1996; 70508 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Organization Drive Bills, 1959-1970; 70507 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Organization Drive Bills:, 1971-1990; 70506 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Dinner: Giovanni Leone, 1974; 70505 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Dinner: Sandro Pertini, 1982; 70504 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Dinner: Testimonial Dinner to Count Carlo Sforza, 1949; 70503 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Earthquake Relief, 1963; 70502 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Earthquake Relief Funds: Donations, 1976; 70501 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Earthquake Relief: Tour, 1981; 70500 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Economic Integration Summit, 1991; 70499 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Enemy Alien Classification Act, 1942; 70498 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Ente per la Storia del Socialismo e del Movimento Operaio Italiano, 1946-1978; 70497 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Executive Committee, 1980-1986; 70496 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Fasanella, Ralph, 1990; 70495 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Four Freedoms Award, 1944; 70494 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Four Freedoms Award, 1945; 70493 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Four Freedoms Award, 1951; 70492 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Four Freedoms Award, 1957; 70491 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Four Freedoms Award, 1961; 70490 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Four Freedoms Award, 1963; 70489 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Free Trade Union Institute, 1987-1992; 70488 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - ILGWU, Local 189: Correspondence, etc., 1934-1944; 70487 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Istituto F. D. Roosevelt, 1948-1972; 70486 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Istituto F. D. Roosevelt, 1973-1980; 70485 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Immigration History Research Center, 1982; 70484 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Italian American Democratic Leadership Council, 1986; 70483 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Italian American Institute to Foster Higher Education, 1982; 70482 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - IALC Contributions & Donations, 1967-1989; 70481 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - IALC: History, 1941-1983; 70480 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Italian Hospital, 1965-1975; 70479 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Italian Hospital Society, 1973-1983; 70478 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Italy: IALC Delegation, 1978; 70477 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Italy: Order of Merit, 1979-1980; 70476 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Italy: Politics, 1968-1979; 70475 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Italy: Trip - Educational Committee, 1954; 70474 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Italy: Trip, 1958; 70473 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Italy: Trip, 1961; 70472 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Italy: Trip, 1963; 70471 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Italy: Trip [ILGWU Local 89], 1967; 70470 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Italy: Trip [ILGWU Local 89], 1969; 70469 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Italy: Trip [ILGWU Local 89], 1971; 70468 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Italy: Trip, 1973; 70467 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Italy: Trip, 1978; 70466 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Italy: Trip, 1981; 70465 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Italy: Trip [ILGWU Locals 89-48], 1983; 70464 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Italy: Trip [Canceled], 1985; 70463 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Italy: Trip, 1987; 70462 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Italy: Trip, 1988; 70461 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Italy: Visitors from, 1978-1989; 70460 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - LaGuardia Memorial House, 1981-1982; 70459 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - List of Officers, 1978-1991; 70458 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1964; 70457 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1965; 70456 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1966; 70455 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1967; 70454 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1968; 70453 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1969; 70452 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1970; 70451 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1971; 70450 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1972; 70449 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1973; 70448 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1974; 70447 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1975; 70446 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1976; 70445 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1977; 70444 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1978; 70443 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1979; 70442 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1980; 70441 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1981; 70440 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1982; 70439 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1983; 70438 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1984; 70437 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1985; 70436 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1986; 70435 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1987; 70434 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1988; 70433 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1989; 70432 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1990; 70431 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1991; 70430 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1993; 70429 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Luncheon (Four Freedoms Award), 1994; 70428 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Luncheon: Dr. Giuseppe Lupis, 1969; 70427 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Luncheon: Dr. Vito La Rocca, 1962; 70426 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Luncheon: Reunification, 1958; 70425 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Luncheon: Testimonial to Egidio Ortona, 1960; 70424 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Luncheon: Testimonial to Dr. Vito La Rocca, 1962; 70423 (Box 5, Folder 16a)
  - Luncheon: Testimonial to Giulio Pastore, 1955; 70422 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Matteotti Assassination (Pamphlet by G. Modigliani), 1945; 70421 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Matteotti, Circolo (Open Letter to Fortune Pope), 1956; 70420 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Matteotti: International Symposium, 1975; 70419 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Molisani Memorial, 1987; 70418 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - National Italian American Coordinating Association, 1975-1987; 70417 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - National Italian American Foundation, 1978-1987; 70416 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - New York City Central Labor Council, 1989-1993; 70415 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - New York City Central Labor Council, 1994-1996; 70414 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - New York State AFL-CIO, 1992-1995; 70413 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Noto, Mario, 1975-1979; 70412 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Order Sons of Italy in America, 1988-1995; 70411 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Parola del Popolo, 1969-1980; 70410 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Pernicone, Santo, 1988-1994; 70409 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Publicity, 1980; 70408 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Queens College, 1979-1983; 70407 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Sevola d'Italia, 1979-1980; 70406 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Spilotro, Nicholas (Bio.), undated; 70405 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Stratiesky, Barbara, 1965-1971; 70404 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Turismo di Ritorno, 1980-1986; 70403 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Unione Italiana del Lavoro, 1980-1986; 70402 (Box 5, Folder 37)
- Series III: Photographs, Media
  - Photographs, 1947, 1987-1997 (Box 6, Box XOS002)
  - Video: John D. Calandra Italian American Institute/Queens College/CUNY & FIERI National Tribute to Vito Marcantonio, 1998-01-18 (Box Shared Tamiment 013, Cassette 11)
  - DVD: CGIL L'archivio nella rete La rete nell' archivio, 2007 (Box Shared Tamiment 004)